Guide to the Stanford University, Board of Control, Graduate Manager of Athletics, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Board of Control, graduate manager of athletics, records
1904-1915
SC0507
Stanford University. Board of Control. Graduate Manager of Athletics.
0.75 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer from the Dept. of Physical Education, 1965.
Information about Access
None.
HISTORICAL NOTE
The Board of Control was established by the Stanford University Board of Trustees in 1905. It assumed the functions previously held by the Athletic Committee of the Associated Students and the Training House Corporation. Its membership consisted of two members from the Faculty Athletic Committee and two alumni elected by the Executive Committee of the Associated Students. Scheduling and financial management of athletic team events was handled by the Graduate Manager of Athletics, who reported to the Board of Control. It functioned until 1917, when the Board of Athletic Control was established.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
These records of the Graduate Manager of Athletics consist primarily of correspondence and financial records pertaining to the scheduling of athletic events and the upkeep of athletic facilities. There are also a few records of finishing times from track meets. The managers represented in these records are Richard Watts Barrett, class of 1904; Guy Knupp, class of 1907; John Elmer Stewart, class of 1908; James Ernest Thompson, in attendance 1907-1911; and Arthur Warren Ambrose, class of 1914. Correspondents include the student groups and athletic managers at UC Berkeley, University of Santa Clara, University of Colorado, University of Nevada, University of Oregon, Pomona College, University of Southern California, and other schools. Non-collegiate teams include the Olympic Club and the Barbarian Rugby Football Club of San Francisco, the New South Wales Rugby Union of Australia, and the Vancouver Rugby Football Union of Canada. Other correspondents of note include James Lanagan (coach), Frank Angell, Stanford professor and member of the Faculty Athletic Committee, the Pacific Coast Rugby Referees Union, and the Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association.
Most of the collection pertains to football and rugby but other sports such as baseball, basketball, and track are also represented. In addition there are scattered items pertaining to the marching band, the glee club, and other activities of the Associated Students.
Arrangement note
The materials are arranged chronologically, with an additional alphabetical breakdown in some of the correspondence files. The alphabetical breakdown is not always by correspondent, and may represent the school, the place, or the sport.
Access Terms
Ambrose, Arthur Warren.; Angell, Frank, 1857-1939.; Barbarian Rugby Football Club (San Francisco, Calif.).; Barrett, Richard Watts.; Intercollegiate Conference Athletic Association..; Knupp, Guy.; Lanagan, James.; Olympic Club (San Francisco, Calif.); Pacific Coast Rugby Referees Union..; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Sports.;; Stanford University. Associated Students.; Stewart, John Elmer.; Thompson, James Ernest.; University of California, Berkeley. -- General subdivision--Sports.;; University of Southern California. -- General subdivision--Sports.;; College sports--United States.; Rugby football.
Collection Contents
- Barrett, R. W., correspondence, 1904-05 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Knupp, Guy, incoming correspondence, A-D, 1907: (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Knupp, Guy, incoming correspondence, E-H, 1907: (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Knupp, Guy, incoming correspondence, I-P, 1907: (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Knupp, Guy, incoming correspondence, S-Z [includes one outgoing letter], 1907: (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Knupp, Guy, incoming correspondence, A-Z, 1908: (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Stewart, John E., correspondence, with UC Berkeley and the Pacific Coast Rugby Referees Union, 1908-09: (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Stewart, John E., correspondence, A-D, 1908-09: (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Stewart, John E., correspondence, E-M, 1908-09: (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Stewart, John E., correspondence, N-R, 1908-09: (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Stewart, John E., correspondence, S, 1908-09: (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Stewart, John E., correspondence, T-Z, 1908-09: (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1911-12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1914-15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence and miscellaneous records, circa 1910-13 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Bills and financial records, 1907-1908 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Bills and financial records, 1907-1908 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Financial records, 1907-1908 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Financial records, 1910-1912 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Meet results, 1910-1915 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)